William N. Wysham Papers
William N. Wysham Papers
1920-1962
Wysham, William Norris, 1890-1982.
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts and published material of the American clergyman, author and missionary to Iran
2922546
Biographical History
William N. Wysham (1890-1982) was an American author, clergyman, and missionary to Iran.
William Norris Wysham was born in Baltimore, Maryland on 10 Sep 1890. He was educated at the Baltimore City College (A.B. 1908), Lafayette College (1913), Princeton University (M.A. 1915), Princeton Theological Seminary (1916), and he received an honorary doctorate from Coe College in 1932.
Wysham was a missionary to Iran (Persia) under the Presbyterian Church in the United States from 1920 to 1923, and again from 1925 to 1938. He was the executive secretary for the Western area of the Board of Foreign Ministers in the Presbyterian Church. He lectured on missions in the San Francisco Theological Seminary and taught in the departments of English and Religion of Alborz College in Teheran, Iran from 1920 to 1923 and again from 1925-1938.
Wysham was a member of the Board of Directors of the American Christian Literary Society for Moslems, as well as of Phi Beta Kappa and Sigma Alpha Epsilon and the Benham Club at Princeton. He edited numerous books and wrote many pamphlets in the Persian language, and was a regular contributor to religious magazines including The Presbyterian and Presbyterian Life.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William N. Wysham Papers consists of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts and published material.
Correspondence contains a series of letters from Wysham at the American mission in Teheran, and a letter from Henry Luce to a Mr. Rosengrant about one of Wysham's books.
Subject files contains pamphlets by Wysham, reports by him, and a statement of the I.L.C. Sales Account.
Manuscripts contains typescript copies of essays by Wysham on the state of Christian education in the Middle East, personal reports by Wysham, and manuscripts for several articles and books.
Published material includes a book edited by Wysham, three published pamphlets, and newspaper articles about Wysham.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. All other material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Religion and philosophy; Wysham, William Norris, 1890-1982.; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. -- Board of Foreign Missions.; Christianity and other religions -- Islam.; Missionaries -- Iran.; Islam -- Relations -- Christianity.; Iran -- Religion.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Pamphlets.; Reports.; Missionaries.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William N. Wysham, 1964, 1967, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing, 1920-1936 (Box 1)
  - Of others (Henry Luce to Mr. Rosengrant), 1952 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Pamphlets by
    - Bulwark for Tomorrow (Box 1)
    - Doors (Box 1)
    - Into All the World Together (Box 1)
    - Is Protestantism Second-Class Christianity? (Box 1)
    - The Missionary Candidate (Box 1)
    - Toward an Ecumenical Mission (Box 1)
  - Reports by
    - Christian literature distribution in the Middle East, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Intermission literature of Persia for the years 1930-1937 (Box 1)
  - Statements, financial
    - I.L.C. sales account, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Book, Christianity is Like That, circa 1962 (Box 1)
  - Christian education in the Middle East, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Christian literature in Persian from 1925-1931 (Box 1)
  - "The Passport and the Pistol", 1921 (Box 1)
  - Personal reports
    - 1926-1929, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1933-1938, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Itineration trip to Demghan, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Itineration trip to Mazanderan, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Itineration trip to Mazanderan Province (Box 1)
  - "Some Vicissitudes of Jesus as a Person" (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Books
    - Memoirs of a Centenarian, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Magazine articles by
    - in Five Continents, 1937; 1947,; undated (Box 1)
    - in Missionary Reviews of the World, 1924; 1926,; 1928,; 1932 (Box 1)
    - in Presbyterian Life, 1954; 1957,; 1959 (Box 1)
    - in Women and Missions, 1924; 1925,; 1932,; 1947 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1925; 1927,; 1936,; 1943,; 1944,; 1959 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings about
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets by
    - Counsel to New Missionaries, 1925; 1948 (Box 1)
    - Measure of a Modern Missionary, 1925 (Box 1)
    - On This We Build in the Near East, undated (Box 1)